His struggle for fame was over. His fight for respect was just beginning.
Tender Mercies is a drama, music, romance film directed by Bruce Beresford.
Alchoholic former country singer Mac Sledge makes
friends with a young widow and her son.
The friendship enables him to find inspiration to resume his career.
Mac Sledge, played by Robert Duvall.
Rosa Lee, played by Tess Harper.
Dixie, played by Betty Buckley.
Harry, played by Wilford Brimley.
Sue Anne, played by Ellen Barkin.
Sonny, played by Allan Hubbard.
Tender Mercies is a 1983 American drama film directed by
Bruce Beresford and written by Horton Foote.
It stars Robert Duvall as singer-songwriter Mac Sledge, a former country music star whose
career and relationship with his ex-wife and daughter were wrecked by alcoholism.
Recovering from his affliction, Sledge seeks to turn his life around through
his relationship with a young widow and her son in rural Texas.
The supporting cast includes Tess Harper, Betty Buckley,
Wilford Brimley, Ellen Barkin and Allan Hubbard.
Financed by EMI Films, Tender Mercies was shot largely in Waxahachie, Texas.
The script was rejected by several American directors
before the Australian Beresford accepted it.
Duvall, who sang his own songs in the film, drove more than 600 miles (1,000 km) throughout the state,
tape recording local accents and playing in country music bands to prepare for the role.
He and Beresford repeatedly clashed during production, at one point prompting the
director to walk off the set and reportedly consider quitting the film.
The film encompasses several themes, including the importance of love and family, the possibility of spiritual
resurrection amid death and the concept of redemption through Mac Sledge's conversion to Christianity.
Following poor test screening results, distributor Universal Pictures made little effort to publicise
Tender Mercies, which Duvall attributed to the studio's lack of understanding of country music.
The film was released on March 4, 1983, in a limited number of theatres.
Although unsuccessful at the box office, it was critically acclaimed and
earned five Academy Award nominations, including for Best Picture.
At the 56th Academy Awards.
Tender Mercies won Oscars for Best Original Screenplay for Foote
and Duvall won the Academy Award for Best Actor.
The film explores themes of country music, guitar,
texas, alcoholism, southern baptist.
The tone is emotional.